[Music]
all right hello and welcome to actin
flab
live stream number 37.1 free energy a
user's guide it's february 2nd 2022 2
2 22
20 days till the big one of course
welcome to active inference lab
we are participatory online lab that is
communicating learning and practicing
applied active inference
you can find us at links here on this
slide
this is recorded in an archived live
stream so please provide us with
feedback so we can improve our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome
and we'll be following good video
etiquette for live stream maybe people
can raise their hand visually so there's
not a little jitsi blip until we figure
it out or either way
go to activeinference.org
if you want to learn more about
participating or check the coda link
here
okay
today in 37.1 the goal is to learn and
discuss and
also appreciate having stephen mann the
first author here with us this paper
free energy a user's guide
and for
this 37.1 we'll start with an
introduction and then we'll just
fire up some
slides and
hear perhaps an opening and a
contextualizing statement from stephen
to be introduced last and then go into
whatever questions that everyone else
has brought and anyone watching live
so
i'm daniel i'm a researcher in
california and i will pass it to stephen
hello stephen i'm a practice based phd
researcher i'm based in toronto and i'll
pass it over to
dean
good morning everybody i'm dean i'm up
here in calgary um
i'm
somebody who does
did some programming
went from being an educator to a
wayfinder
and i find guides really
an interesting topic to have
conversations around i'll pass it down
to blue
hi i'm blue i'm a research consultant
based out of new mexico and i will pass
it to the first author stephen
hi everyone i'm stephen i am a
philosophy phd
currently a postdoc at the in the
linguistics department of the university
of surrey and a guest at the max bank
institute for evolutionary anthropology
in leipzig where i live
all right
maybe stephen would you um or stephen m
would you like to
just give a little context on the paper
like how did this fit into your
phd or research interests how did this
specific collaboration come to be in the
format of the paper and the way it is
sure first uh thanks for having me and
thanks very much for last week's session
with dot zero i think you did a really
excellent job at uh overview and i'm
really looking forward to talking about
it today um
this paper came about because
we
uh myself and ross and michael the other
authors
had been in discussions
with a few other authors
around a symposium discussing active
inference and the free energy principle
and also uh predictive processing
at the
australian society for philosophy and
psychology conference in 2018 uh we put
together a small symposium
it went relatively well and
after a few more months of sort of
passing ideas back and forth
we approached michael weisberg the
editor of biology and philosophy about
putting together a topical collection
sort of like a special issue but sort of
um
collected digitally
and
eventually sort of after sort of
pitching it to him and managing to
get to talk to him in person um he said
that he and the other editors were quite
excited but what they wanted was
an introduction from us that would
explain the mathematics
and the philosophical
dialectics
behind sort of at the core of active
inference in the free energy principle
in a way that was accessible for
philosophers
and so we said sure we can do that and
that was a little while ago we started
soliciting alpha papers we've now
published most of the papers in that
topical collection
uh and since then
uh
at the same time sort of finalizing
finishing off my phd and then moving to
europe from australia where my phd was
we were getting to grips with the real
mathematical core
of uh active inference and trying to
figure out
what was the necessary mathematics to
explain the basics of the framework
and then how to present that mathematics
to
a philosophical audience who has sort of
some mathematical competence
and the result is the current pre-print
so we think we're probably about one
more set of revisions away from uh
submitting for publication and it will
eventually come out as the introduction
to that uh topical collection so what
i'm really interested in hearing from
everyone else today
uh
this the same thing we're interested
from hearing from the wider community
which is the reason we release the
pre-print which is just comments and
suggestions and any kind of corrections
that can help improve the paper um so
that its final form is sort of even
better as good as we can make it
okay thanks for the awesome context
stephen s
thank you yeah um we're really enjoying
this paper and one thing it'll be
interesting to
to think about even though you you sort
of aimed at maybe a philosophy audiences
some of the aspects of it
at this nascent kind of foundational
level
could help in an applied context that
may be
beyond the modeling
so we're kind of interested in some of
that so that might be something we might
tip into even if it's not
in the remit of this paper's
direct publication i think it would be
really helpful
in the broader sort of journey of using
active inference in the world
awesome
okay um
blue
or dean
would you like to start with a question
or we can return to one of the points
that were already kind of brought up
i'm good for now
um
okay
so
maybe just one starting point was just
what backgrounds like
how did you
go from thinking about who you wanted to
make the paper accessible to
to writing it a certain way and then you
mentioned it was for philosophers so
what is the impact in this
community
that you'd like to how would you like to
update their generative models
nicely put
first and foremost
we would like to fix in their mind the
relationship between
uh
variational inference and bayesian
influence
so i know that's something you've uh
talked about before it's something that
pre-dates the free energy principle and
active inference as an explanatory
framework for cognitive science and
biology and it's something which
as far as i can tell is sort of the the
first step in understanding
what's going on with that mathematics
um
so that's the sort of the key thing we
want
philosophers to sort of have in their
minds also because
almost all philosophers especially
philosophers of cognitive science but uh
but also philosophers of biology will be
familiar with bayesian inference at
least to some extent so by pointing out
that what active inference is is
something sort of a step to the right of
bayesian infants something that they can
start to understand by analogy with that
we hope it will stop them from sort of
getting scared of all the complicated
mathematics that you can read in a lot
of the papers
um
so that's on the math side on the
philosophy side a lot of the stuff in
section four of the paper was our
attempt to really strip back
a lot of the claims that were being made
but also
sort of categorize the claims being made
one thing that i noticed in reading the
literature and attempting to understand
it
was that
different kinds of claims were being
conflated
and there was jumping around
from claims in different domains
mathematical claims that suddenly uh
leverage to justify an empirical claim
and then suddenly move to an extremely
general claim about all of cognitive
science or all of biology in general
so
that's the second thing we want the
philosophers to get that it is possible
to disentangle these claims despite the
fact that they are habitually
sort of conflated or not made distinct
enough in the rest of the literature
all right one follow-up and then i see
stephen and dean um you mentioned that
bayesian
inference may be more familiar
especially because it's used in all
kinds of modern statistical descriptive
approaches as well as generative
just to hear it in your own words where
do you think variational inference is
more familiar so who does it represent
who's more familiar with variational
methods or who would be familiar and
then what are the key differences
sure so my understanding is that
uh
physicists statisticians and machine
learning practitioners
uh may well have come across variational
inference certainly will have had a much
better chance of having come across
variational inference than philosophers
at least as of 2022
what i understand variational inference
to be is a certain kind of
technique for choosing a probability
distribution over unobserved
uh
states
that started uh in physics as i
understand it with feynman although
i put a little footnote in the uh
pre-print pointing out that i haven't
been able to translate the stuff in that
feynman book to the later stuff
especially stuff that um
david mckay talks about in his textbook
on
information theory which includes some
issues in variational inference but as i
understand it started in physics
then was adopted into sort of statistics
more broadly
as a means of approximating bayesian
inference in cases where exact bayesian
inference is too difficult to carry out
to computationally difficult
and then move from statistics into
machine learning where it's possible to
actually
build machine learning algorithms or
systems that can perform variational
inference and then from there it ended
up being in the active inference
framework
all right thank you so dean first
stephen thanks for joining us i really
appreciate it um
here's a question for you
now that now that uh
an examination of the situation and the
situation
as you stated was kind of
uh math and um philosophy
have now i've got a relationship and
we're going to up out pops
a guidebook or a primer
when the when the pump is primed what do
you see as being the effect of that
that relationship between the
sort of philosophical audience and the
and the math that was used to get us to
this place
relationship between
the philosophical audience and the math
that was used to get us to this place i
mean
first and foremost
i want the philosophical audience to
gain a certain kind of facility with the
maths
i think
one of you i'm not sure who of you it
was but in the point zero
put it extremely well by saying it's
like learning how the horse moves in
chess
i think it might have been daniel but i
don't want to miss attributed to you
giving the philosophical audience the
basic understanding of the most basic
maths
will give them that first kind of tool
which they can then go on if they so
wish to build up and learn more of the
moves learn more of the complex maths if
they want to then go on and interrogate
the rest of that literature which is
more complex
we've tried to sort of
forego too much critical analysis in the
paper there is some in there
um we've tried to forego that a little
bit just in order to
get the understanding of that maths
across
okay
i can follow up there
um
what does it matter for
the philosophers so what are they
in your sense or
their sense
what will knowing the difference between
bayesian and variational help them
evaluate
or what will seeing it structured this
way help them evaluate
i think there's a few so i hope other
people also can think of philosophical
questions that
knowing the difference between the two
would help you change your mind on
yeah i mean
the simple answer is just it will help
them understand what fristen is claiming
and by fristen of course i'm using him
as just an umbrella for anybody who's
writing uh positively in the active
internet tradition attempting to
demonstrate that the active inference
framework can provide or inform certain
process theories that uh explain
cognitive or biological systems
philosophers need to know the difference
between bayesian inference and
variational inference because they need
to know
uh what it is that fristen is claiming
can be attributed to systems like this
okay blue on that
so i have a question and um like maybe i
missed it and i was looking i just did
like a quick control off on the paper
just to make sure that i didn't miss it
and i'm not like misinterpreting but
um in your explanation of um
the generative model like i just wonder
why you didn't choose to
go into the recognition model and i
think that like while you've discussed
at length like p's and q's
why did you leave that out or do you
think it's not significant or did i miss
it and did you talk about it
[Music]
so by the recognition model i understand
that to be a sort of alternative way of
doing inference that uh an agent could
employ
so i'm just i'm saying what i understand
by it so you can correct me before i try
and answer the question
uh i understand it to be
yeah an alternative to generative
inference is just to employ a kind of
recognition model which simply takes in
data and immediately produces some kind
of statistical result from that data
it doesn't need to uh simulate or
generate its own data and then compare
that to what it sees that'll be the
generative way instead it just
applies some kind of say mathematical
statistical function to the data and and
then gets a kind of result
which describes what it hasn't observed
is that what you meant by recognition
model
oh no so i'm referring to um the paper
the tale of two densities the 2019 paper
by brampton al and um you know in that
paper they they refer to um
the recognition model as the q right the
inverse of the likelihood model it's the
mapping from the consequences to
the hidden causes and so like you you
got really into the maths
but
and discussed the the um generative
model but just didn't um like
acknowledge this this recognition model
and i just was curious
as
okay so you just mean the the
distribution
queue
uh by by the recognition model
um
am i using a different queue i haven't
read a tale of two densities i should
say so
uh yeah
the recognition model is on the it's um
in the uh kind of namespace of
expectation maximization
modeling the recognition model is like
the sensory update
and then the generative part was like
emphasized i hope that's not
too simplified or what two densities
were and then that outbound was more
like associated with the generativity
and that's also um that's why it's
important to go from the frequentist to
the bayesian at all
because with
bayesian generative modeling like the
model can be run both ways
though it's used with different
adjectives
that's like variational autoencoder
that's um
all these methods where it's not just
descriptive modeling on a data set like
principal component analysis or multiple
regression it doesn't just describe then
it can be used although those can be
used
or be thought of as bayesian like can be
used in a generative way as well but
that's the part that people will have
less empirical experience
seeing but
let's
think about this and then return to it
next week
um
yeah okay so stephen s
just following on um from the bayesian
um
which
is often used in the embodied
context people think about embodying and
multi-sensory integration and that type
of work and that field
is a bit challenged by moving over to
this variational machine learning
paradigm because it's highly
mathematical but what's interesting with
active inference it sort of comes back
into
that being grounded in embodied action
because that gives the preferences
somewhere to be anchored so how do you
see
um this going back into
embodied cognition
as a way for those preferences to be
grounded
uh that's a difficult one
uh for me to answer in part because
i'm not really part of the
tradition that emphasizes
embodied and enactive
uh approaches to cognition
[Music]
the way
i was taught it they were sort of
alternatives to the representationalist
tradition and i was much more the
representationalist tradition
so
there has been some talk of whether and
how
free energy approaches support one or
the other of those two traditions
uh
and
to some extent because i'm already
sympathetic to the representation of
tradition
i'm already leaning towards the idea
that uh free energy approach will
support that you know as opposed to an
embodied or an active kind of approach
which is sort of a shame because
like all of those kinds of binaries it's
probably somewhat a false dichotomy
and it just means that you know my
direct my attention has been directed
elsewhere than your attention in looking
at these issues
um
and so yeah i don't
have enough value to add unfortunately
i think it yes stephen
but um
our previous paper 36 was like
a taxonomy of perspectives on the
representation question in fep so i
think we're all
very
primed to just take it totally open
stance and
is is every possible stance for every
person to focus on
it's just kind of
not within our
time and attention capacity so i think
it just speaks to um like a diverse
field where of course people are
focusing on
chemistry of
this element of that element it won't be
exactly that split but
in the broadening field of like active
inference and fep
there's gonna be people who are focused
more on one question or other so that's
kind of cool to like know where we um
have similar regimes of attention or not
stephen
yeah i'm agreeing with daniel and also
actually we found this really really
helpful from an embodied perspective
because
the way that you separated or you gave
the probabilities and preferences of
working together
was um
it was kind of like a deflated or a more
nascent form of representation and that
jives quite nicely
with
potential ways that
inactive approaches are also potentially
there because the nature of preferences
so you start to have a way where they
can both live together
because we i don't know we were talking
about this the other day won't be daniel
that that it wasn't so clear how these
two
can live together and often when people
who are from philosopher quote the free
energy principle they talk about early
papers like 2000 and
you know maybe 10 years ago even and
that
is often then a false argument gets
painted so now we've almost got a new
paper which can kind of
help
ground those philosophers so i wonder
what your thought is in terms of whether
you're trying to help people use the
most latest form of free energy
principle when they were talking about
philosophy and to stop some of the
conflation of just people criticizing
models which are now out of date
um
if that was part of your rationale for
the way this paper was created
yeah we absolutely wanted to direct
people's attention to what we thought of
as the
real issues in a way
the the appropriate issues
um
i mean we reckon that
a critical assessment that is not well
informed by the actual workings of the
theory is not going to be helpful
because
you might accidentally hit on a critique
that works but only accidentally if
you're going to criticize a framework
you better at least understand what's
going on
um
my worry is that
it will become out of date as things
change but there's not a lot you can do
about that i mean it took us quite a
long time to get this
first draft together to get this
pre-print together and i'm sort of
hoping that things haven't changed so
much that it's out of date by the time
it comes out uh i mean one way to foster
all that is to just be as basic as
possible so that you're really capturing
the core that can't possibly you know
change
um
but otherwise your best chance is just
to
publish what you've got at a particular
time and keep your eye on how things
change and update as you go
thanks yes dean
stephen if
i use a lot of metaphors so if you
walked into a singles bar and one of the
singles was a philosopher and the other
single was a mathematician
and you had to guess now going through
the process of building that guy right
like you're not match.com but right you
have to make a guess as to whether that
long-term relationship they walk out
hand-in-hand or they're completely
repulsed by one another
i know it always depends but you're
talking about updating the guide i'm
kind of want to go back
one previous step what keeps them
together
what pulls them apart
yeah so how do you
write what is essentially a philosophy
paper but include mathematics in a way
that does justice to both
is is roughly how i'm hearing that
question well a long-term relationship
right like they still got to have some
compatibility
and the feeling right until its point
was
up to now it's been i don't know if i
even want to go to the bar
so
that's that's what i'm asking you know
based on what you've
what you've journeyed into right because
not everybody i know i unders i
appreciate the idea of the guidebook
because
not everybody goes into situations
right sometimes you get dropped into
situations and it's a little bit more
intense but what causes people to go
freely into that kind of uh relationship
and sustain it over
a long enough period that it does make
sense
doesn't remain kind of a superficial
thing or just a concept but it actually
becomes realized i was curious what your
thoughts on that are
hmm
i think that
you know trying
hard not to repeat myself too much uh
the way i the way i try and think about
that question is to try and think about
what has prevented philosophers from
really accessing the
mathematical parts of active inference
so far and that's just from sort of
communicating with philosophers and
talking to them and hearing their
dissatisfaction with it and it was
always just that there was there was too
much of it too fast
and so the the sort of the only approach
we could see
that could remedy that
was to go
as slow as possible
in a way uh and so spend sort of
have a much
heavier ratio ratio of
word to equations in a way
and go into much much more depth in
explaining each equation as it comes
along
uh rather than
throwing all in at once and then
decomposing it
right i mean we
one of the earlier versions of the draft
we started with the main equations and
then decompose them in the current draft
that you've read
we start with the components
and then build up to the main equation
that was a little bit risky i thought
because i was worried that people would
feel we were holding the main event back
for too long
but
so far it seems to be working i'll say
i'd be interested to hear your thoughts
on on that approach
whether you think that meshes together
well enough yeah no that that's one of
the things
and again i don't think mathematicians
are trying to be pushy but if you don't
have that context it can feel pushy
and so
how how long you're willing to leave
something open before you
drop
drop the big questions is sometimes
easier for somebody then to size the
situation up and contextualize it so if
in this in this delivery i don't know
previous versions
right but in this delivery in in that
respect i actually think it makes it
less intimidating but that's just my
that's my personal opinion sorry stephen
i know you wanted to say something
steven yeah
stevens
yeah just carrying on from what dean was
saying as well is
um you you looked at the inference model
almost prior to having a markov blanket
you know and i thought that was quite
useful and one thing that that may made
me think as i was reading it and i'd be
interested in your thoughts is
it it helps with this idea of really
thinking about where how are we going to
create the blanket when does the blanket
come into play and what assumptions are
there about the blanket in some ways
it's easy to pick up a pre-built idea of
what blankets are and then model off
that was it's like okay well let's
question that and that actually could be
useful at your a more heuristic
level you know for other fields of
practice so i'd be interested in your
thoughts about
what you think
your motivation for that and also maybe
the sort of
surprising or unsurprising outcomes of
not going straight for the blanket
well one of the big revelations for me
in researching this paper was that
you can talk about variational inference
and you can talk about um minimizing
expected free energy
without talking about markup blankets i
had sort of come into this with
uh just sort of a huge deluge of
literature from the active inference
tradition
lots and lots of like key words
well what could more uh
uncharitably be called buzz words like
markov blanket and
non-equilibrium steady states and things
like this and
it was a concern that i would first have
to understand statistical physics and
fluid dynamics before i could understand
the claims that were being made about
inference but looking back into the
history and you realize that first of
all variational inference
is a precursor to active influence so
you can think about variational
inference in its own little bubble as we
have it in its own little section
and then the sort of next step which is
novel and is quite excitingly
novel
um which is minimizing expected free
energy can also be construed just in
terms of decision theory you don't as
far as i can see you don't have to think
or talk about markov blankets
at all to talk about
decision theory as
minimizing expected free energy
so the reason why we separated them was
because they're separable the reason why
we put those two first variational
inference and expected minimizing
expected free energy is because i think
they are simpler and easy to grasp and
we were trying to start from the simple
and build up to the more complex
it's i think it's definitely true that
the most sort of intriguing and
possibly the most sort of difficult part
of understanding this whole
system which fristen is building is
understanding the things to do with
markov blankets in real like physical
situations
um but
what i'm sort of interested in now to
give you a preview of what i'm like
thinking about next the more
the thing which i'm more optimistic
about being able to make headway on is
investigating minimizing expected free
energy as a decision theory that sort of
gets the middle ground between it's not
just something that prefigured active
inference as variational inference did
it's not something that seems to require
a very large amount of mathematical
understanding as the mark of blanket
stuff does seem to to me
it's something which is claimed to be a
certain way of approaching decision
theory decision theory sort of a
philosophic philosophical sort of
technical term or a statistical term so
it's that nice middle ground between
novel but understandable
um which is why the yeah the thing that
i'm sort of most
interested in investigating next is
the expected free energy approach and
again i don't think you need to talk
about markov blankets to talk about that
right
okay thanks for sharing that one thought
um on
where the markov blanket comes in
so you said that variational inference
and the minimization of expected free
energy
in the context of a paper that was
structurally laid out with first
perception
and then introducing action into the
loop so it kind of
fits
this perception of case as like action
affordances are not possible
and so that's the special case the more
general case is when action can come
into play
that whole
realm
of
action theory decision theory game
theory cybernetics
signal processing
none of that
it was said requires the markov blanket
formalism
i'd like to maybe add that there may be
a weak sense requirement like in the
sense that on a bayesian graph or using
bayesian methods
using pearl
version of the markov blanket
there are markup blankets in the
machinery of these bayesian methods
because there are variables that are
isolated or conditioned on each other
so that's like the trivial markov
blanket the non-contentious one that
people are not spending a lot of time
and attention on
that
and then part of the unknown or at least
less clear
is the
action and perception
interpretation
or concordance that fristen has
introduced kind of taking the unitypel
markov blanket concept and splitting it
into like an incoming sense state
dependency and outgoing action state and
then
none of that gives a clear action
perception topology which is why we've
seen like around the clock and then
where the ones like action and sense are
connected and backwards arrows
so
there's the part about the partitioning
of the markov blanket and then
taking something that's kind of a
trivial consequence
of statistical models
and then tying it to potentially realism
in the strong cases
like people saying mark up blankets as
defining things
and then even just within the formalism
how do you go from how do you
ramp up the meaning
of this markov or does it need to even
be that way
which is kind of related to this
question which i'll ask and then anyone
can give a thought like you talked about
necessary and sufficient
so
is this
some of the necessary and sufficient
pieces of
fep what is what is necessary like
what's the kernel that everything else
can
continue to elaborate around
what section and page number please
well you'll notice that we were cheeky
in defining three distinct
free energy principles probably none of
which would be you know ascended to by
the actual proponents of the free energy
principle um
yeah exactly um
could you go through and just describe
in a few like sentences or just what is
each one of these the three free energy
principles inference action selection
what did they mean to you
first one free energy principle for
inference as you know as we've defined
it is
when
dating your sorry my cat is biting me
now
sorry i'll hold him up here so it
doesn't bite me arm
um well the short version is
choose q by minimizing f
so
choose your beliefs about hidden states
by minimizing variational free energy
so that's uh it's a principle in the
sense that philosophers would call
a normative principle it's a command
for how to act in this case the specific
kind of action that is how to choose
your beliefs
okay
and uh free energy principle for action
also a normative principle telling you
how to act
and this one is uh in our again in our
terminology choose zed
by minimizing g
so choose your action
by minimizing
its expected free energy
this is all for anybody who's watching
this who hasn't looked at the paper
we've
tried to sort of describe um
in very slow
but understandable way what what these
different sort of letters are standing
for
me give the definitions for a discrete
case
okay so
we have perceptual inference
bayesian expectation maximization like
choose q the member of the variational
family distribution by minimizing this
snapshot f
based upon your priors
basically and new information coming in
and then that takes on a normative
interpretation it's kind of like saying
if you were doing linear regression you
would do the l2 norm least squares
if you're doing this type of
regression
then
do this kind of inference
the second one is also normative but
it's action theoretic because you
introduced action and then that
introduced the elaboration on f to the g
function
um
maybe stephen s
how would you say that this movement
into the future
first
matters for maybe not necessarily how a
philosopher but how um
any other relevant area might see this
in an applied context like what does the
f to g
movement have to do
well i think it's i think what's useful
is that it's like it's almost taking
what's evolved out with the markov
blanket with the
expected free energy and bringing it
back down
into a more
a form which isn't only a form which is
involved in
the modeling out
of
particular systems at low
dimensionalities come in and say okay
this is a broader principle that can be
talked about
and i think that then
ties into some of the stuff the active
inference lab is trying to look at is
how can active inference itself be used
as a way to think of organizing and
structuring our lives like george perek
might have thought about it and
how
can it be
used as a heuristic
in in areas like coaching psychology in
areas where you're looking at action
orientated
decision support
in complex evolving
ways you know
so you can't
you can't model it in the in the
traditional sense of a marker because
there's nowhere near the dimensionality
can be approached
so
what's useful is they say okay look
we've got these general ideas we've got
a route to it but that there's the
general deflated forms of that
actually
then because they're not so high order
and they're not so
nailed down to one idea of a mark or
blanket maybe has a more universal
application when someone's trying to
look at complex contexts and how to act
in the in the world
so i know what your thoughts on that but
that that's that's what i'm very
interested in is this idea between sort
of
diagnostic kind of syndrome-based
psychology and
how do we look at actually what's going
on in a context look at the
the symptoms look at the context
unfolding and work on modeling using our
own
apparatus as dialogical
sort of collaborative
human beings
stephen uh uh dean first and then
stephen m if you want to give a thought
on that and we're just gonna talk about
this inference in action piece because i
think there's a few more pieces to draw
out and then we'll get to the third
selection but dean go for it
yeah so back to my strange twisted
metaphor so now all of a sudden applause
for walks into the bar
and instead of one one map showing up
we'll call it the geometry which is
much more amenable to the model
in terms of how a philosopher might walk
into a space
and see the geometry first
uh all of a sudden there's two maths
there's a statistical math that's that's
showed up at the same time are they
twins what's going on here and i think
that's where the guide
is kind of handy because if you first
walk into the space i'm
i'm not arguing that a markov blanket
exists i think relationship matters but
i think what most people that walk into
that bar
don't realize is that you're walking in
on two
different maths
and they're both showing up at the same
time when you were expecting one
you were expecting to be able to work
with a model
which is
as i said it's far more proximal to the
geometry
math than to the statistical one
and so i think that again when we're
talking about guides
um
i don't have to i can put my hand in the
ocean and figure out what the current is
and i can look up at the stars and
figure out where i am in that invariant
space
i don't necessarily have to have a
laptop
with the statistical distribution i mean
that might help but that's not a tool
that i needed first hand
whereas i think the modeling part which
is what you were
were trying to bring up with this guide
is at hand
and so it's the availability piece that
i think
philosophers are trying to are trying to
what what
what did i walk into here that's
essentially what am i walking into and
what is the betweenness of those two
types of math
that they're probably if they're like me
but i'm not a philosopher they're asking
when they're when they're being
introduced to this so i'm just curious
again if i'm if i'm going way off on a
tangent or if we're introducing
something we actually know what we're
being introduced to
and that's the part we stephen used to
talk about slowing down because i really
agree it's not a breaking down it's an
actual
slow down
nothing wrong with that whoa
i mean i could try and approach an
answer by sort of extending your
metaphor if you'll give me license to do
so
imagine you're going to the bar
and there's dozens or even hundreds
of
maths or different components of maths
or different approaches to maths
and
what you'd really
like
is some way of paring that down
to something that is approachable
you you know that only a few of these
will be approachable but you don't know
which ahead of time
i'd like to think that you could use
what we've written as at least the first
step to pairing some of that away so
what we've left out essentially is the
stuff that you could pair away and say i
can't approach that yet
what i know i can approach is these
first few things
and
what i like to think is that we've
done
okay at getting at least some of those
first few things
in there
you know not too much not too little
just really trying to find that gold
lock zone and those will be the ones
that are approachable even you know
approachable for a philosopher
who's met very little mats before um
i know i owe stephen s a response to
your earlier question as well but if you
want to go ahead
first stephen or daniel you'd say well
yes steven s go for it yeah i'll just
say maybe bring up slide 13 if you're
able to daniel because that might be a
useful one
just as it has
i have it
yeah
cool
because it's that's got a little bit
there about the penalty for overfitting
penalty for failing to explain the data
um and that that has 13.
oh is it oh i said maybe i'm looking at
the numbers at the bottom okay but
on um
page 23
or oh yeah
35 here yeah yeah okay yeah slide 21
yes
yeah this definitely juxtaposes the the
f and the g
it's like a pokemon evolution
but it includes those different pieces
about bringing in action
with uh
the
uncertainty on the consequences of
action
and the fundamental
um
and the ability to impact it
but that was actually what i had um
kind of written down so stephen made the
point about how action is a lower
dimensional space
and
that's like
making it an algorithm tractable like
conditioning inference on action which
is something that's very different
structurally than a lot of other control
theory where the target of inference is
a policy selection
here the affordances play a little bit
of an upstream roll and they make the
downstream calculation conditioned on
action
so that speaks to a different
embeddedness of action in active
inference
and then
um
there's a few other things but first
stephen m what would you what was the
answer that you owed at the other
stephen
yeah i mean i was really just picking up
on the the point that stephen made about
the difficulty of accurately
modeling
and we talk about this a lot in
philosophy of science i mean the
philosophy of any of the special
sciences but in the sort of philosophy
of science more broadly one of the
biggest topics
is modeling
and one of the biggest questions is
how do you trade off between getting a
model which is a perfectly accurate
representation of the thing that you are
modeling
versus something that is tractable and
that you can handle and the analogy is
always made with
maps that's sort of the first analogy
you can't have
a map that is an exact replica
replica excuse me of its territory
because you wouldn't be able to use it
to navigate it could not provide you
with anything that was more helpful than
the territory itself
so
we have some kind of
practical knowledge of how to make maps
we know what to leave out we know how to
condense it we should at least you know
shrink it usually
if we're creating a map from from a
territory what we don't really have
in a very general sense across all of
science is
a set of principles for how
given a specific situation that is too
complex
to produce a perfect representation of
what all you leave out and what all you
keep in and how should you transform
that space into a representation of that
space in order to produce a
representation that is a useful uh
approximation of it
so the question coming you know back to
the formalism would be
how do you choose a kind of a q
distribution your approximate
distribution the thing that you're going
to harbor in your brain and believe
that throws out enough of the useless
stuff
of the real world but keeps in enough of
the stuff that you really need to keep
in in the world
this is sort of the
one of the big questions
in philosophy of science and i guess
science proper at like the early 21st
century
awesome answer thank you dean
and then blue
yep just real quick so
daniel when when daniel talked in the
point one about
the third p
but he called it the p h i t n e s s the
the fitness that's what basically
you're describing how do we take that
that
variance
field and collapse it down to something
more
tractable as you
said and so at some point later on
either either later on today or in our
next live stream i think that's
what the active inference model
which is not a map
and it has probably two parts it has a
frame but it also has a it also has a
filtering effect maybe we can talk a
little bit about that because that's
that's what the fitness
is really about so i'm looking forward
to sort of diving a little bit deeper on
that because it's not just
a back and forth across
and and reaching edges it's actually
going
deeper into it and then returning from
so
yeah i'm kind of looking looking forward
to that from a mathematical standpoint
as well
thanks dean blue
so that's the perfect like segue fitness
um and into what i was going to bring up
and so um steven something that you
mentioned earlier is like your
attempt to
capture the essence of the fep and the
things that will not change
and kind of build slowly incrementally
and and so
if we have a theory that does not change
essentially like does not
evolve it will die like it will become
extinct because we're constantly
learning new things and so
i mean i think um
i i
like from a counterpoint
think that it's kind of critical to
capture the evolution of the fep over
time because
it really um changes the the potential
applications and um
ways that that people interpret the the
principle and the theory of active
inference also
and so what like if it doesn't change i
mean
will it not ever change or is it subject
to change or just what are your thoughts
on that like like is it totally
inflexible these these points that
you've attempted to lay out
no i mean yeah that general point is
very well taken indeed um
i i guess i think that
uh by
trying to capture something that we
thought wouldn't change i think we meant
or i should have said
we're trying to capture the parts of it
that
the rest of the framework
will continue to depend on
um
for sort of as long as possible we tried
to keep the most stable parts of it
without necessarily implying that
active inference could survive without
these mathematical components but just
that
the change to the theory or the change
to the approach would have to be so
radical
once you've got rid of these core
mathematical components that someone
could legitimately ask is it still the
same theory
so that's roughly what i would mean by
essential such that
if for example
tomorrow fristen were to say we don't
need to talk about variational inference
anymore or we don't need to talk about
minimizing expected free energy anymore
someone could legitimately ask okay is
he now talking about a new theory that's
no longer active inference
is it so different because he's thrown
out that sort of fundamental part that
he's now actually proposing something
completely different
um i think that someone could
legitimately ask that question i think
that a reasonable person could say that
he's now talking about a different
theory because i think that those
mathematical parts are so
uh crucial to it as opposed to some of
the other parts which seem
some of the more complex parts seem more
dispensable you could throw out some of
the more complex things keep these more
basic things and
you would still more likely be having
the same theory
yeah blue
so just to respond quickly like so
for me that's kind of an arbitrary line
in the sand
um
and like one thing that we've talked
about back and forth a lot is this
concept of ergodicity and like an
ergotic system versus like a
non-equilibrium steady state density
locally ergodic like what does it mean
and is the if we throw out every density
and eliminate this requirement like is
the theory still the same theory and and
so like that's one point but i mean
there are many points um in like the
minimization of free energy and and so
on and so forth and so
as we add on to
the theory
we are changing the theory all the time
like as new papers come out like the
recognition model versus the generative
model and you know bayesian mechanics
for stationary processes was kind of
really highlighting a couple key uh
points but as the theory goes and
changes
it's like at any point we could say well
that's not the same theory and so if
you're if you're
so the theory is not allowed to evolve
over time like it's just this arbitrary
point in the sound that that you don't
want to cross like the minimization of
free energy what if we decide that the
minimization of free energy means
something totally different like even in
this paper
i mean you had in a footnote um about
the complexity versus accuracy but but
to refer to free energy as inaccuracy is
like i've not heard of it described that
way before and so for me i mean
it is this complexity and accuracy and i
understand like the um the way that you
framed it but it's a completely like
novel way to talk about free energy like
i always hear about as here here it is
framed in terms of like uncertainty or
surprise but not inaccuracy like that
was completely like cop took me off
guard actually so i mean as the theory
evolves like i don't know it's just
what are the what's what's the
irreducible component of the fvp like
does such a thing exist or is it just
turtles the whole way down
yeah you're asking me the really hard
questions i like this because it's tough
it's really tough to think it's honestly
yeah it's tough to think and answer that
and to to ensure that i'm answering sort
of honestly as to what i really believe
as opposed to just trying to sort of
dismiss what you say uh
you know i i'm not
trying to dismiss what you say i do
think
that the line is
blurry so it's not clear and distinct i
don't think that it's arbitrary i might
be wrong in that but i don't believe
that it's arbitrary um
let me just leave to the side for a
moment the the description of free
energy as
inaccuracy uh i'll come back to that
because i'm interested in picking up
what yeah what you think about the
different interpretations of of the
function f um but i'll try and go back
to sort of the idea of
herbicity
uh
yeah there's a sense in which
things are still being worked out and
one of the things we put in the paper um
is something that we were urged to
make clear which is that
active inference is a work in progress
even the sort of mathematical
underpinnings are
still being
fleshed out in a sense or still being
put together in a way that helps connect
the different parts of the theory okay
that's okay that that in fact was a
little bit difficult for me to swallow
at first because i felt that if that's
true then it doesn't legitimate all of
the strong claims that are being sort of
made but all of our complaints about
that are in that fourth section of the
paper
so we try to make clear what we think is
sort of justified and not justified on
that basis but it's still true to say
that it's fair to have a framework and
to you know to expend time trying to put
together the mathematical underpinnings
of this framework uh even though they
don't yet exist you know we don't have
to
we shouldn't just throw out the theory
or disparage it just because the full
math hasn't been worked out yet i agree
we should allow it to change we should
allow it to evolve we should allow it to
be
applied to different things and see what
works and what doesn't
with all that being said i i don't think
in this particular case maybe it's true
of other theories but for active
inference
i don't think that it's true
that there are things that you could
remove
and still reasonably say
yeah this is still active inference i
think i think
a theory
could not be that amorphous and still be
sort of treated seriously as
uh as a way of pursuing science
i think that you would have to say
if you threw out minimizing variational
free energy or you threw out minimizing
expected free energy or some other of
the core components
i think you would have to say if you're
being reasonable again the word
reasonable is doing a lot of work in
this paragraph that i'm building up to i
think you would have to say okay it's a
different theory i think you'd have to
say okay we were wrong to pursue the
minimization of variational free
inference a variational free energy as a
principle for understanding the behavior
of biology and cognition we are wrong to
pursue that we're going to pursue
something else instead and so you
couldn't just say oh it's still the same
theory but we've changed this core
component of it i don't think that line
is arbitrary i think there are some
things that if you change
you have to sort of admit that you're
wrong about that approach and go on to
something else
that's sort of my piece uh i've talked
for a really long time i do want to pick
up the idea of free energy as uh a
function that measures inaccuracy but i
don't want to talk for like a huge
amount of time so maybe i should put a
pin in that and we could potentially
return to it later
how about um first free energy selection
stephen m
finish that
three then as in accuracy and then um
then i have a point
right great yeah i forgot we were only
two thirds of the way through our
descriptions of the different free
energy principles i'm sorry uh so free
energy principle for selection uh let me
try and pull it up here so i can just
read it directly off the
page
uh what we have it has is any system
that survives long enough
will act so as to appear to be
minimizing f
one of the issues here is that we've
left out g but
for the sake of sort of focusing our
attention we can just talk about f
okay
and then how about the fep as uh or
free energy as inaccuracy interpretation
great yeah so this is um
this is something that
i was hoping would be again a way to
present it to philosophers so that it
would be easier for them to grasp what
was going on i wanted them to understand
why do we care about this function f why
do we care about variational free energy
well suppose that i tell you that in
order to do inference what you ought to
do is minimize variational free energy
and then you could very well say why why
should i care about minimizing these
things and then if i tell you oh it's
the measure of the cost of inaccuracy in
belief then you immediately say okay i
understand why i would want to minimize
that because i want to maximize my
accuracy
so
very simply put it's a way of explaining
why we should care about f
it's a measure of inaccuracy um i think
that interpretation holds up just to the
extent that if you look at the two
components
um which can be sort of thought of as
you know a cost penalty for overfitting
cost penalty for being inaccurate
there's a part of that which is
inaccuracy
it's not the whole story of course
because the other part is to do with
complexity not just to do with accuracy
so
what i think we've done by describing
free energy as a measure of an accuracy
or the measure the cost of inaccuracy is
trading off that sort of ability to
enter into understanding the maths
for
you know a perfectly clear
mathematically very precise way
of describing it
but i think i definitely think that it
should be thought of as containing a
term which is a cost of inaccuracy
so we talked in the dot zero about it's
kind of like finding the shape from the
data and the fineness of the mesh
and inaccuracy in the real world kind of
has elements of both or at least we're
used to thinking about complex decision
trade-offs like you could make a bad
decision because it took too long but
then you came to the right outcome
in the scheme of thinking bigger than
just one p-value and so it's kind of
opening up even this
very kernel piece of the puzzle
to the whole question of how specific
and how many subgroups
and always leaving space for not
overfitting given this whole map
territory
porges
and would you say that the the
overfitting inaccuracy
um
you know is more around when you talk
about adaptive active inference where
there's a way to
adaptively
look and have an idea of beliefs in some
way
and that
underneath that there could be a kind of
a
more
abductive
swarming kind of
entropic kind of process
which
is sit in the background but in terms of
how we normally explicitly think about
meaning we would think about it more in
terms of what can be
understood as beliefs so just be
interested how that how you see that
from a philosophical point of view
well one of the things that's still
unclear to me about the
overfitting part of f is that
it seems that it can only be interpreted
as sort of a cost of complexity
if what you already believe is simple
because what it's really measuring is
how far you are straying from
what you already believe
so that there's kind of an implication
there that
everybody always has
simple beliefs in the first place and
that therefore they ought not stray from
those simple beliefs
one of the things that i'm trying to
think about now is
what happens if
you are starting with sort of more
complex beliefs
maybe that's not a sort of appropriate
question to ask given the framework or
the way we're supposed to interpret the
maths but i can't help wondering it
given that
it strikes me that you know in order to
interpret it as a penalty for complexity
you have to say
you have to assume
that what you're starting with is
simplicity and i guess there would be
real life situations in which you you
don't start with
simple beliefs
and then presumably this would tell you
well if your beliefs are complex then
they ought to stay complex because that
penalty is a penalty for straying from
that kind of complexity
which seems
you know
different from how it's usually
described
yeah steven s um
and would you say that that that falls
into our more recent
move
from science as
creating models and fitting things to
those models
like in the most simple way
to be in modellers
like with post-normal science and even
pristine's work with the covid
so
there's a belief in engaging with a
complex non-resolvable
system
question which is different to
science's traditional role which is to
have an answer and to fit things to it
well one of the most exciting and sort
of scary aspects
of active inference
is the idea that it's applied
not just as a way of understanding what
our target systems are doing so not just
as a way of understanding what a
biological system or a brain that i'm
studying is doing
but also as a way of understanding what
i myself am doing when i
represent that target system in order to
try and understand it you get a kind of
loop in a way
in a sort of sense in which you you feel
as though you could model your own
activity by using
these
technical tools which active inference
is giving you
but then you feel like
how could that be done in a way that
doesn't invite any kind of infinite
regress that's why it's scary as well as
exciting it's exciting because it seems
to potentially provide some kind of
extra power or insight into our own
activities as scientists or as models of
any kind but it's scary because it seems
to then drop you into a kind of
spiraling hole of the modeler who is
modeling themselves modeling themself
etc
that's something which i can't think
around even informally let alone try and
get to the formalism of it
that was the very structure of
paper number 36 so even in its
qualitative application
just at the terms and concept level it
does
turn the mirror back and that is
speaking to
um the pre and post or pre post trans
distributional aspects of active the um
all the funny things that dean says as
well
and the strange loop there
so what that made me think of is like
the statistics
and then the famous quote like the
statistician can come in for the
post-mortem or something like that
but a lot happens before the statistics
happen
like the design of the experiment and so
the optimal experimentation
and then the knowledge that it will be
passed through a distributional filter
in the big
macro of the scientific method
like
planning months in advance for how many
minutes and hours
one is going to count insects or how
many microliters of fluid they're going
to move that is sort of the
implementation phase and then there's a
design time and so that's also what ties
science to engineering in a way that
hasn't been in design thinking in a lot
of other areas too
dean
yeah this is awesome so
i mean one of the things that we talk
about is some of those density questions
around what's
what's the linear aspect of it and
what's the solenoidal aspect of it and
we also talk about walking into a
room of mirrors with a mirror suit on
i mean it all comes together in the
sense that they're i think one of the
things that steven mann pointed out is
that there are i think they're
one of the things i think we can say
about
active inference that's consistent is
that it has at least a minimum of two in
that back and forth
up and down the density
bump and around the density bump you can
go either direction
and
so that
that has me asking whether when every
time we we say that this is a framework
whether we're only giving it half it's
due
whether it's a framework and also a
filtering exercise like does there have
to be a minimum of two not just the
boundary but then what is actually going
on dynamically within that border
so that we know when we're crossing when
we know when we're within the boundary
that we've maybe are looking at
empirically right because we selected
our unit of analysis but then when we
know when we've crossed outside that
when we've
when we've gotten to a place where the
mesh
is holding certain things back while
other things that are of a smaller
circumference are still able to sort of
pass through
and so
i think as a as a guide
um that question of as we model
as we model the model is the minimum
i think if we just say the model
we don't do it justice and if we just
look at the as we model
the act of doing that i think again
we're looking at sort of
a side of beef and expecting to be able
to milk it and i don't think that that
works i think you have to have the whole
thing
or else you don't really have active
inference so
[Music]
that's
i think that's kind of where we're at
when we're coming to the place where
we're trying to decide what goes in
and what doesn't go into a guide
and it's a struggle right like there's
no there's no question it's probably one
of the hardest things that you can do
because
the majority of people that are guides
are there because
they've been there before versus the one
who hasn't
and that would require upending that
that basic premise which is
no everybody has to get into the boat
and we're sailing off onto the onto the
event horizon
that would be the only way that we would
change that so the actual nature of
guides would only change if everybody
had to get their skin in the game
and start at that basic place of not
knowing
but that will leave that for another
another
another live stream but at this point
that's what's really interesting here
one of the assumptions that we made is
somebody has taken the time to go and
exert and explore and come back with
information and the other people don't
have it
and the only way that changes is if
everybody gets in the boat
and sales often hopes that they don't
come to the edge of the cliff and fall
out so
okay
a lot there thank you dean just
a few other points people have different
perspectives on what is core or not some
of the uncertainty
let's get at it with the ontology
development and
making some definitions and translations
and the formalisms clear in the history
of science and all of that
but even then it might be pretty
fundamental like if it includes action
and inference
is variational methods necessary
so
who knows
people will have different
interpretations just about a lot of
things and so that's
again all part of the fun so stephen
so one question i'd be interested is
talking about guides in terms of that
book
life a user's guide um
that's a very deep
i read it for a long time and then i
lost it but it's sort of like it takes
you into all these aspects of people's
lives in that parisian
neighborhood and
it never gives you an answer
it doesn't but it in some ways it's
leaving it to your intuition it's
leaving to
your
integration and i'm wondering where you
see that that integration that's
happening at a non-perspectival level
the integration the intuition the the
affective consciousness
that is part of our knowing
and
how that
relates to this and maybe if it's even
something that's not part of science but
is part of this kind of
work
well i mean firstly you sort of crack
the code in a way because the title of
the paper was directly and explicitly
stolen from the correct book
um
it wasn't
necessarily a sort of uh
the best like joke
because it's not
it's in a in the sense in which the book
is about an incredibly hyper-specific
and detailed description of
a system you know an apartment block a
specific time point on a specific day
uh of the year
gave me the idea about okay it's like it
it's not true that we ever really
represent things that way it's not true
that science intends to represent things
that way in the way that perek does and
he's sort of making fun of but also he's
he's incredibly constrained in the way
that he wrote the book as i understand
there's some
there's some really crazy games that he
plays with language in writing it and
the course for example translates a huge
amount of difficulty in translating it
because how do you know how do you
translate the game that he's played in
french into a game you can play in
english while writing the english
version of the novel
so
definitely the idea of
representation
and sort of naturalism was on my mind
but the sort of the short reason we
called it that is because we wanted a
punchy title we wanted something that
people would think was accessible
um
but definitely when it came to casting
about for punchy and accessible titles
that was the one that primarily came to
mind
um
when it comes to sort of
affective consciousness and sort of
experience again it's
it's a little outside my wheelhouse i i
was very very
impressed upon
by the novel even just in english
translation because i can't read french
i was really
really sort of moved by it in various
different ways
you know intellectually emotionally
things like that
there's a lot about sort of
representation in there just the concept
of representation
uh and that's something that i'm you
know interested in but again that pulls
sort of in the opposite direction from
an activism or effective consciousness
and things i'm very very much
situated in that kind of formal dry
approach to philosophy the kind of
analytic tradition where we try and chop
things down we think we're scientists
you know inspecting the human condition
under a microscope
um and so but you know i can't
deny that in reading a novel it flows
over me in the same way you know i'll
experience it in a similar way that you
experience it i hope
yes blue
so totally funny um i was also had a
question about a guide but like
on the opposite of like life a user's
guide i was reminded of the movie
beetlejuice um and they like the couple
dies and they have this like handbook
for the recently deceased right and like
the the core of like the theme that they
could well did you read the guy well did
you read the guide and it's apparently
like a very thick dense book like that
no like you can't i mean we're dead you
don't know what to do we're freaking out
we don't have time to sit down and read
this book and so um i i was reminded of
that just kind of totally juxtaposition
but it's like when you are creating a
guide
it's very difficult to like make it
usable right like the map versus the
territory like what
what will people read and be able to
take away and walk away with some kind
of general understanding versus like if
you really want to know what to do when
you're dead in this situation you've got
to read the book um you know how to like
haunt the house and all these things and
so
like do do we really need to like full
grip of the fvp to really sit down with
the guide you know whatever like
3 000 page
manual
or like where how do you distill the
essence of something that's so
complicated like what is it to be dead
or what is the fep right it's hard
that's such a good example
like it's a handbook for the
handbook for the long-lived the i guess
the free energy principle as opposed to
handbook for the recently deceased
uh yeah what what is the the line that
they have in that it's something like
some incredibly dry statement which is
absolutely no help at all like
operational parameters vary from
manifestation to manifestation or
something and yet i mean the idea behind
it was that
the philosophers that we talked to that
urged us to try and research and write
this
we're pointing out that when they
attempted to read
those papers in the active inference
tradition even those that were billed as
tutorials it was like trying to read the
handbook for the recently deceased it
was if not too long then at least too
dense
and they couldn't pick apart
those statements because they were too
condensed and so yeah the difficulty
was
un condensing it pulling it apart
selecting what was necessary and then
presenting it in an accessible way i
mean
all says that it took sort of on the
order of years to do it we we sort of
got commissioned as it were in
2019 i started researching it in earnest
at the beginning of 2020
and the first pre it went through a few
you know drafts and people gave us a lot
of comments behind the scenes but the
first preprint came out in december 2021
so
yeah it's
for me at least and for us the authors
it was that
difficult to
troll through the literature find what
was necessary and then present it in a
presentable way
but that's such a great example thanks
so much that hadn't crossed my mind but
i love that film and the concept of the
handbook as well
so just a few comments on that it's not
called free energy principle a user's
guide
it's actually very specific it's about
the variational free energy and the
expected free energy f and g
respectively
what's the fep
so that's sort of
where it takes you and it's very subtle
then um
that was pretty interesting handbook for
the long lived and
it reminded me about metacognition in
learning
and about what we expect and prefer and
think we can know
and how like just being a
um
learner and like a teacher's assistant
seeing how there'd be lecturers
that would give um
maybe it could be thought of in sort of
an effort g framework another day but
they would simplify
and learners would have high precision
on a very simple model
and then other times they would um
convey too much of the complexity and so
at the end of the quarter even if the
students learned a ton and
they would still feel like lost in a
bigger space
and there's like good and bad aspects of
all of that so uh
i think this is kind of like a snapshot
it's kind of cool that it is so recent
that was only a few months ago right
now that it's february 22
but this is very like recent in and
still kind of ongoing that you're
looking to update it too
so it's sort of like a kind of window
where there's interactions with the
community and hopefully people
really think about it and
um the people for whom a section isn't
clear have an opportunity through this
affordance we have now as scientific
publishing with preprints like to
ask or correct or you missed a citation
here
that is awesome and it's a world apart
from sort of
three people with it on their desk who
are delaying it in review
and then maybe they have good comments
maybe they don't
but here there can be something that's
so much beyond that as this is just like
one thing that you're working on and
you're developing
and then one last comment on that is
like
spm the textbooks are still kind of
classics cult classics we might even say
and it's not that the notation
hasn't changed a lot because it has in
some cases it's a snapshot
and
there's some amount of linking back to
the past
that's clarifying
and then
there can be an understanding that
there's drift and focus and evolution of
the techniques and the spm textbook it's
going to have sentences that you
wouldn't include if you're writing it
today
great
that's why it's different but also
there's something about it that helps
inform so every snapshot that's well
intended always is good dean
yeah i think one of the other things
that's really interesting about this is
this
stephen m has
kind of pointed to the the length of
time when the question was posed
can you
can you summarize this for us can you
synopsize this for us
basically what the philosophy it sounds
to me is what the philosophers were
asking was can you go and do
the figuring out and then present that
to us in a finding out way will you save
us
time
and so i think what that's one of the
things we have to keep front of mind
when we look at this because those
philosophers now didn't do the two years
of heavy lifting and searching and
foraging
there's that's a whole different aspect
that figuring out
is a whole different processing method
and mechanism than the finding out
right and so again if you want people
if you want people to come away
from guide use
with more than
the finding out they're still going to
have to get in the field and do the
figuring out themselves and it's that
interaction part which
thank thank goodness for blue and
beetlejuice because that was again that
was just a wicked
example right because it the timing of
this the windness of this
really really matters
and i know that in a lot of educational
settings time is at the essence right 13
weeks x number of hours blah blah blah
we tend to get that we tend to that's
the only part of the oneness that we
focus on not
should the guide or the plan be the
thing that initiates all the action or
is that the thing that falls out
afterwards if we're doing figuring out
it has to fall out afterwards
not before
and we have a really hard time
with that because traditionally it's
always been
the legitimizing of guides because
they've been there before
and they'll help you find out but they
don't necessarily
help you figure out
just because the amount of time
yes please stephen m
i mean yeah so both of the things that
you both just said daniel and mendeen
like they're both open up huge topics
which
uh have so many interesting questions
and so many interesting ways of
approaching them um
dean
i i think i agree 100 with what you just
said
uh
they've done the
they're going to have to use our guide
as a kind of shortcut in a way to doing
that initial stuff they're finding out
but
it behooves them in a way to do some
extra work of figuring out afterwards
the the thing that that most sort of
resonates with me
regarding is just the idea that
our like mandate what we had to do in
producing this
was
give them the ability to work through
like the examples themselves because
that's a part of
i mean
you know i'm not sure how you're
distinguishing these two things but to
me that's a part of figuring out as well
as just finding out
to me we're not just saying
this is a measure of inaccuracy
and this is the algorithm by which you
minimize it we're saying look at this
example with these numbers
you know in the imaginary situation and
if you work through it and if you you
know print out the graph yourself
you will find that this is where the
minimum lies for example and you will
compare that with this other thing so
we're doing the sort of the the first
tiny step in helping them figure out how
they would figure it out in a way if you
see what i mean giving them the the the
means to go ahead and do it again
themselves in a different kind of
situation
but the sort of the other thing that
it brings up i mean
i shouldn't say that you know they they
like michael weisberg didn't say you
know go and do this for me go and be my
like research assistant for two and a
half years to print this thing
uh he along with uh peter godfrey smith
who is another person uh not connected
with the journal in that capacity but
very interested in having this framework
explained for a wider audience
pointed out that first and foremost
we ourselves would get some kind of like
plaudits for having done the work having
helped people to understand it so you
know there was the personal selfish
incentive to do it
um but also that it would be
something that
would benefit the community in a sort of
in a positive way not something that we
would be giving them
for free as it were but something that
we would be creating for everybody to
draw and use and just improving how the
community approaches this question
so in the same sense in which you know
in in the best case academia is a
wonderful collection of people who are
all helping each other
to
you know find those shortcuts
do the finding out without going through
however long it takes
to sift out
the the stuff that is not necessary
we're all helping each other to do that
you know i can read somebody else's
paper who is working for two years or
something completely different and
having
split up that
labor
divided that labor up we can both sort
of benefit from it
um
sorry i'm going on far too long now no
no no one i'm only answering one
question one last thing about the
minimum of two things if we could get
you you and connor heinz
into a live stream i think my mind would
be blown just because that math and this
philosophy in one proximal
location because that that to
triangulate off that
would be
amazing
because that's essentially what you have
to do you have to put the finding out
and figuring out together
i don't think again i don't think it's
one or the other i think it's our
ability to sort of be able to hold up
both at once and appreciate how each of
those things fills in the picture
yeah and i do want to thank you you
should tell me when i should uh stop or
you know please just jump in and
interrupt me anytime but you know i just
wanted to sort of respond to your points
as well um
the other good thing since i'm in an
optimistic mood about academia uh like
you say the kind of pre-publication
pre-print
sending it out and enabling people to
give us comments back on it
if you think about it like is that
metaphor with going into a classroom and
teaching before you go in and teach you
have to pair away all of the nonsense
the stuff that's too complex get it down
to the level that's simple enough so
they can understand but has enough
information so they can actually learn
something
in the really good case of getting a
kind of course evaluation you do a whole
course you get a bunch of students tell
you what was right what was wrong with
what went too fast what went too slow
you know and hopefully there's a kind of
average where it averages out and you
improve it sort of next time you make it
easier for the learners because the
learners
have told you what was right and what
was wrong about it it's always that kind
of feedback process obviously in real
life situations
it doesn't always work that well getting
that kind of feedback um but if you're
sort of lucky enough to start off from a
decent point as i think we have at this
paper
you can
you can get to a kind of point which
once it is snapshotted because that's
the other important thing i think that
this kind of pre-publication peer review
is really useful but the
there shouldn't be constantly evolving
documents all the time there should be
some kind of snapshots once it's
snapshotted it's like it's as good as it
can be at that time
even if it becomes redundant eventually
even if it uses language which won't be
used in 10 20 years
once it becomes something that people
can refer to valuably for some kind of
certain amount of time afterwards that's
really the best that you can hope for so
you know
certainly for you know just a paper this
is just a paper it's nothing
uh more than that really
just one thought on that like on the
finding out and figuring out connecting
that to the peer review it's almost like
we're all co-learners
in participatory engaging education
so we want to make it easier for the
learners which is us
and we're all co-learners so sometimes
we find out
that would be somebody with more domain
expertise
giving us the feedback on the paper and
then in the side channel maybe there's
another time and place where it's a
different
roles not relationship but like and then
there's the figuring out and then maybe
there's other things here too that's
actually
um not like feedback from the bottom up
but beginners questions
abductive logic applications adversarial
or contrarian even questions that is
always like what is active inference
why does f matter
um what
does the fpp have to do with active
inference
what does
evolution have to do with natural
selection what does natural selection
have to do with drift
if those were not resolved
then
they're going to be some open ones in
this area as well
and i think there is also another
analogy with sort of like
uh in a um concordance with evolutionary
theory
and like darwin's dangerous idea done it
in 95 that type of book
um perhaps has already or soon will be
written for something like fvp because
it has that same ability to like spawn
an adjective
and then re-integrate the adjective back
into the corpus so it was like there was
like evolution of this type and then
people add like a modality or a
sub-domain or a new word and then it
joins the main thread so we have like
deep affective
sophisticated contrastive dot dot but
it's going to reintegrate
because
it will be versioning and that
returns to like blue's point about what
is core
what isn't and how will that change and
so
and then you just kind of close the loop
with the snapshotting but the
recognition of the process
but we have to make the static
modification in the niche but of course
it's a process so
it's really um
interesting where we've gone today
yes stephen m and then s
oh yeah just very quickly uh
i think the point about contrarian
questions is a very
good one um it's often
philosopher's main method of figuring
something out
beginning with
the contrarian question that is
uppermost in their mind going out and
trying to find the answer to it
and certainly in this case um on my side
when i was doing my part
of writing the paper um
i was starting with
what on earth is this maths
and what is the interpretation of these
different components of it
um
and that was just for the for the maths
when you get on to the sort of
philosophy side the interpretation the
dialectic
i mean one thing i haven't said is that
there are some quite skeptical portions
of
this paper you probably you know noticed
when you read it and
we tried to you know pull back a little
bit but what we wanted to do was
provide
fuel for figuring out
and you always want to try and do that
in good faith you know you always want
to do it in a way that's not combative
or dismissive
you want to do it in a way that is
uh
designed to help you and the person that
you're asking
come to a consensus about the answer
thanks steven okay steven s yeah i i
really find this helpful this
fortuitous use of the term guide because
you chose that title which maybe
if you weren't doing a pre-print maybe
pete i noticed people a bit more
creative with the titles which um
then that's maybe also a nice benefit
but by going there this discussion has
been really helpful i'll be i often hear
people when they talk about the findings
from research that oh we're going to
roll out a toolkit we'll do a tool kit
and then when they talk about a guide
it's really a sort of a guide a guide to
teach the tool kit
and but here the the what in a way
you're looking at especially if you're
getting into the more
deeper tacit knowledge is what's the
guiding principles to being a modeler
what's it about being a model and that's
where well these kind of conversations
are useful but i think that
the the type of
stuff that's been brought up here are
things where
you know
they're not resolved down to a toolkit
level
but it opens a question for someone to
have a conversation about and so i just
thought i'd mention that and
what your thoughts are about that
challenge of
someone becoming
a practitioner
rather than necessarily an academic
disseminator
yeah it's tough because i'm really not
sure
in part because
all that i'm sort of
trying to be right now is
an academic disseminator
so i would have to shift into a sort of
different gear to think about what it
would mean to be a
practitioner um
i mean i i would start by asking
you what you
take being a practitioner to be and then
see if i can you know
resonate with something in that
well for me it's um
it's more contextual and it's more about
being able to adapt and
evolve based on a situation
and often you find the practitioner work
is when you're in a face-to-face
performative context in a way where you
have to perform
either the the dialogue i suppose in
science when you're in the field of
practice
in other areas it could be
the performance of giving a performance
um be a performance as a as a teacher
could be a performer being an actor
being a
um
a workshop facilitator being a therapist
being whatever that might be
and i suppose that that that question
about
how something being a guide
a toolkit
or some way
to access
um
the sort of heuristics and ways of
knowing which aren't even
representational in the kind of
the way that we can easily externalize
so i suppose there's some of that
there's stuff that we can't take a
perspective on directly because we can't
necessarily encode it into artifacts and
place them in our environment in words
however
that knowing
is a skillful practice
that has been sort of cultivated so i i
kind of feel there's there's a need for
that and there's a there's a big move
towards that now with
um the world trying to embrace
transdisciplinarity
participation
complexity
where you have no way to make any sort
of movement forward without the ability
to
to find other ways to hold the meaning
dean
just to just to sort of piggyback on
stephen i think i think
if you want to try to draw a comparison
if you're a disseminator the result can
often be something like a desire line
a wearing in a following
and if you're looking at the generative
model you're looking at a densifying
at a foraging
and then a an accumulation
and in that in that respect it's it's
quite clear what from a practical
one one's not better than the other but
one results in quite a different
result than the other as something to
think about
and then
one other thought on this um
practitioner and scientist
though i hope we see
a hundred times more and more different
ways to learn and apply active inference
just total first thought would be like
when stephen was describing a
practitioner
contextual and adapting on situations
with really lower levels of control
it's on a continuum but like a crisis or
a transition moment or adversarial
scenario
has a lot of an implicit factor and it's
not always as focused on like the
coolest calmest most collected
stigmargic artifact modification it's
more like
the firefighting was done appropriately
in that scenario given what it was
and then the scientist generates niches
like epistemic niche laboratory niche
computer niche
that allows them to generate scenarios
where they can
apply distributions and then when they
apply the distributional methods where
there shouldn't be a distributional
method
it's going to be
unfortunately a silent error most the
time
because of how
[Music]
little paid attention to
all these differences are
so stephen m
yeah this is
really
tricky to think about i mean i
i think i agree that knowing
ought to be considered a kind of
skillful practice
that was one thing that you said uh
stephen that i
really sort of jumped out at me
uh in part as being not sufficiently
emphasized elsewhere certainly not
sufficiently emphasized in the tradition
of philosophy that i come from there
there tends to be a fairly clear
distinction between
knowing in terms of representational
knowledge and
knowing how in terms of skill and
there's not that often
the consideration of
the kinds of things we would usually
consider representational knowledge as
underpinning a kind of skillful practice
but
when i think about the way that
i'm thinking about
philosophy conferences and the kinds of
conversations that go on it's pretty
clear to me that having a conversation
with somebody else
about a topic that is so sort of steeped
in
law and
intellectual
recognition and texts as having a
philosophy conversation is what it
requires is a kind of skill a kind of a
smooth a kind of automatically picking
out the topics as you go along
not sort of sitting back and thinking
very hard on your own before coming back
30 minutes later and responding to the
things that your interlocutor has just
said
it's it has all the hallmarks of a skill
as far as i can see
and what happens is
well the the way that
i have been brought up to view it is you
do all your thinking at home you do all
your thinking in the armchair and then
when you come out to have the
conversation you're ready with that
skill
because you've done all of that
slow
solitary work first the kind of
propositional or representational kind
of work then when you're ready you come
out and you practice discussing it
thanks great point it's a lot like the
representational
dimension is kind of the non-linear
knowledge model which is cannot be
conveyed in a linear sequence linear
presentation in video and in writing is
rhetoric
and
that was one of the most interesting
areas
in the paper was like the claims
justification the whole second part
and i'm happy that we spent
almost all the dot zero and our
conversation
leading up to it
because there's a whole paper and it
sounds like it there's so much more to
explore
but like
the part about the rhetoric
and the way that people
not just have an edge in their knowledge
graph their armchair knowledge graph or
their relational database not just an
edge between concepts but actually
when a question is raised to move to
that answer first or the first topic
that's mentioned
like if somebody asks what is a markov
blanket
the first
noun
what is it going to be
well for a cell
or is it
because of bayesian
or what is the actual first rhetorical
node that somebody gives
and those kinds of knowledge
like representations are really
interesting too
it's not even just that it's the most
important thing because that's not how
people always structure their speech
so like there's both sides we need the
non-linear part so that we can actually
build a bigger structure than just an
oral
script
but then
it has to be in that like run time that
you kind of described at the philosophy
conference
it has to be presented in a linear way
and if there weren't disagreements or um
like contrast in people's perspective
then
they would just be reading off the same
book
so maybe
we'd love to hear your thoughts on
any of these
latter sections in four
like which one of these areas of claims
we won't
stay long but just
what of the areas of claims
or the relationships between areas was
interesting to you or like
you learned while reading about it
because you had the justifica
justificatory links between dialectical
categories with mathematical empirical
in general
so maybe just one edge or one section of
those what did you find interesting
oh was that an open question or you're
asking me i wasn't sure i guess to you
uh i mean i can definitely start with
the first section which was the
mathematical to empirical direction
uh and as you said we
for each edge of the triangle we were
only sort of considering one direction
mainly for considerations of space
what's most interesting to me about this
is just that it is an established
research field
called computational cognitive science
when when the specific math that is
being looked at is certain kinds of
neural networks or other kinds of
computational systems and the specific
empirical system that is being looked at
is the brain especially the human brain
and what we really wanted to emphasize
in this section was that the kinds of
tools that have already been developed
by computational cognitive science so
that includes the models and the
explanatory tools and the justificatory
or inferential tools
could be applied to active inference
models as well so this was our attempt
to say
to the philosophers we already have
some
equipment
we can use
when what we're trying to do is evaluate
active inference
so whether we call it deflationary or
not there's a lot of
relevance in
emphasizing which parts are specific to
active inference and which ones aren't
like bringing action into the loop
is not
a novelty in the last 15 years
doing bayesian statistics doing
variational inference and so that work
helps us really highlight
the parts that do have unique and
different interpretations
like this is definitely one of um
my favorite paragraphs i think that
we've come across and gotten the
highlight on the discussions like
and then you even brought it up that
it's actually in the distillation
there is a novel
um
not just implicit knowledge or
notational connection but a rhetorical
element that arises and then also one
with like educational and didactic
implications so that's really
interesting dean
yeah and i think when i was reading a
paper stephen i noticed the number of
times you had the word evaluate evaluate
evaluate which again is another one of
those
do you get does this pass past muster
pass
a standard pass what goes what goes on
and what gets held back
what gets continued
attention and what do we now ignore and
that's why i like when you were talking
earlier about
well when we put a guide together we
just want to basically walk into the bar
and make sure that the 98
things that we
really can't pay attention to first that
that doesn't pass
what does pass are maybe these two
these two first nascent
ideas
and so again i
you don't need to even hear this but if
you want a just a factory link
that is one right there in real time in
terms of what what what carries on what
can we build off of
and what falls away
because it doesn't it doesn't seem to
pass whatever evaluate evaluative
methods
we've implied but then again that goes
to
when do we start evaluating from the
from the moment we started do we want it
to be something a little bit more
creative and hold that thing open a
little long before we jump to assessment
okay so
in the last just few minutes yeah
stephen do you want to give a response
there or would you like to have a little
bit of a closing statement
uh
let me give a quick response which is
just that i agree exactly with what you
said dean and um
yeah we wanted to show that some things
could be evaluated very directly
just by working through the numbers
and that gives some directions for how
other things could be evaluated and
you're right it's like passing it's sort
of
how a philosopher evaluates a scientific
theory as being sort of in a sense
uh
first level plausibility or first level
acceptability how it passes that it's
it's kind of a philosopher's technical
term um but i can sort of give
a kind of closing statement uh that uh
calls back to what you just mentioned
daniel that paragraph which is just that
the the thing that i'm thinking about
uh most often when i think about active
inference right now is the
interpretation of p in
the
expected free energy function
and the sense in which it can have
a probabilistic interpretation as well
as an interpretation of a kind of
preference that is the thing which i
really want to try and get to the bottom
of again just by working with very very
simple models try and throw some numbers
around
try and intuitively grasp what that
model can represent we have one in there
with the example of the cap but i want
to try and expand it a little bit
um
[Music]
yeah i'm glad that you like that
paragraph
because it's the thing that is causing
me the most uh
it's the thing that's itching the most
that i'm attempting to scratch right now
all right so we'll each give a closing
thought so just
what did people enjoy
what would they look forward to talking
about next week
so stephen select first
well just thank you a lot for a really
great engaging conversation and uh
lots of insights i i'm really interested
in that idea of
the ps
so
i think that's very interesting and i'd
be interested in how that maybe applies
both on the um
on the sensory side and the action side
so how much is the probabilities
and preferences for sensing
as much as or is it that one is more for
sensing ones more for action but uh very
interested in all of that so thank you
very much and
look forward to more conversations
okay dean or blue
i'll go ahead
um
so thanks for entertaining all my
interrogations i appreciate it um if
you're going to come back next week i
would encourage you to check out um a
tale of two densities because like on
the tail of steven with the p's and the
q's i'd be curious to to
think about or hear what your
interpretation of that is and if you
would um
maybe change or maybe you will i mean
it's just a pre-print so maybe you have
a versioning affordance to kind of
consider that in your explanation in the
beginning i'm curious
or if you think it's one of these
superfluous extra components that is
um for
the handbook for the recently deceased
not necessarily you know like the 13
steps of dying
or whatever
so i'd be curious to hear to hear what
you have to say about that
dean anything
yeah it's just that i don't i don't want
this to drop down to the sort of quantum
level but i think that when you're doing
a guide it's hard not to
sort of try and juggle both the dynamic
aspects
of what you're trying to share and the
stable aspects of what you're trying to
share you want the
you want the screwdriver to remain
robust and constant and then you want it
to also be able to
be manipulated in such a way that it
drives the screw and there's a dynamic
and a stability piece to this this
guiding that's really really hard as you
say square i don't know that it can be
squared i think it i think they both
have to be maintained and so
my sense is is that i
i didn't know
what you were going to do in terms of
the guiding but i think the way that you
laid it out did slow things down
did allow the the teeth of the
screwdriver to get set
and then you could actually do something
dynamic with it
so really appreciate that and maybe
maybe next week we can talk about
when the screwdriver is used for
creative purposes other than driving
screws because i think what the math
if we use the
geometry and the statistics and the
philosophy all in one
concoction i think that's the basis or
the minimum that we have then to be able
to be do creative things and not just
recombinatorial things so maybe we can
touch on that i would be really curious
to hear how you see this going off in
creative ways without going and because
the big fear people have is that just
means destabilization
where i'm saying it has to start from
both stable and the potential to move
thanks dean stephen any last thoughts
just to thank you all very much for
engaging with our paper for inviting me
on the stream for asking me really great
questions and raising great points that
just had never crossed my mind this is
exactly the reason why i was hoping to
do this um i am going to try and come
back next week i can't make any promises
right now because next week is a bit of
a heavy week for us but
just yeah the
the prospect of going and reading that
paper and then just being able to
respond in a more intelligent way to
please question is making me really want
to do it not to mention all of the other
topics which you know we haven't talked
about yet from the rest of you as well
so um i will let you know during the
week um but with fingers crossed
again next week
but thank you all thank you yeah really
appreciated everybody sharing their
perspective and you're welcome back
anytime so
see you everybody peace
you